Guide to the Keith Botsford Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Keith Botsford papers
1890-1969
YCAL MSS 471
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
43.6
(112 boxes)
The Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and other papers that document the life and work of Keith Botsford from the beginning of his career to 1969. Correspondence is both professional and personal, and documents Botsford's writing and editing activity, as well as his involvement in International PEN and the Congress for Cultural Freedom. Writings include corrected typescript and autograph manuscript drafts, proofs and other related material, dating from 1940 to 1967.
Botsford, Keith, 1928-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Keith Botsford, 1964-1969.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Box 112: Restricted fragile material. Reference surrogates have been substituted in the main files. For further information consult the appropriate curator.
Keith Botsford (1928-)
Keith Botsford, European-American author and Professor Emeritus of Journalism at Boston University, was born March 29, 1928 in Brussels, Belgium. He has authored numerous novels, articles, essays and translations, and is the editor of News from the Republic of Letters.
Scope and Contents
The Papers consist of correspondence, writings, and other papers that document the life and work of Keith Botsford from the beginning of his career to 1969. Correspondence is both professional and personal, and documents Botsford's writing and editing activities, as well as his involvement in International PEN and the Congress for Cultural Freedom. Writings include corrected typescript and autograph manuscript drafts, proofs and other related material, dating from 1940 to 1967. Other papers include a small quantity of personal documents and photographs.
Arrangement
Organized into six groupings by series or acquisition: I. Correspondence, 1941-1969. II. Writings, 1890-1968. III. Other Papers, 1937-1968. IV. October 1964 Acquisition, 1906-1963. V. December 1965 Acquisition, 1958-1960. VI. November 1969 Acquisition, 1961-1967.
Researchers should note that material within each acquisition overlaps with/or relates to material found in other acquisitions. In order to locate all relevant material within this collection, researchers may need to consult each acquisition described in the Collection Contents section.
American literature -- 20th Century; Authors, American -- 20th Century -- Archives; Editors; Journalists; Translators; Authors; Editors; Journalists; Translators; Botsford, Keith, 1928-; Congress for Cultural Freedom; PEN (Organization)
- Correspondence, 1941-1969; Series I; 6.67 linear feet (16 boxes)
  Arrangement
  Organized into two subseries: General Correspondence, and Third Party Correspondence and Other Papers.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I consists of the personal and professional correspondence of Keith Botsford spanning the years 1941 to 1969. While correspondence is chiefly incoming, some files include retained copies of outgoing letters. The correspondence documents Botsford's writing and editing projects (including the early years of his collaboration with Saul Bellow), his activities with International PEN, the Congress for Cultural Freedom, and other organizations, and events that Botsford attended.
  Principal correspondents include Saul Bellow, Rolf Fjelde, Helga Greene, Iain Hamilton, John Houseman, Jack Ludwig, Henri Peyre, Lawrence Richardson, Harvey Shapiro, and Roger Shattuck.
  - General Correspondence
    Arranged alphabetically.
    - "A" General, 1953-1969; 3 (Box 1)
    - Allain, Roger E., 1963 (Box 1)
    - Arcigiegas, Germán, 1963-1964; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Asher, Aaron, 1959-1962; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Auerbach, E., 1953 (Box 1)
    - "B" General, 1951-1965; 3 (Box 1)
    - Baccaro, Guiseppie and Ulla Johnsen, 1963-1964; 2 (Box 1)
    - "Banks", 1955-1957 (Box 1)
    - Barreto, Vincente, 1963-1964; 2 (Box 1)
    - Bard College, 1954-1956; 2 (Box 1)
    - Bazelon, Bud, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Bedford, Sybille, 1957 (Box 1)
    - Beisel-Botsford Gallery, 1947-1948 (Box 1)
    - Beisel, Helmuth, 1947-1949 (Box 1)
    - Belitt, Ben, 1951-1952 (Box 1)
    - Bellow, Saul, 1957-1965; 3 folders (Box 1)
    - Benitez, Jaime, 1962-1964; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Berg, Gunnar, 1952, undated (Box 1)
    - Bergman, Charles, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
    - Bespaloff, Alexis, 1958 (Box 1)
    - Beyer, Ulli, 1962-1963; 2 folders (Box 1)
    - Bondy, François, 1961-1964 (Box 2)
    - Bor, Matej, 1965 (Box 2)
    - Botsford, Anne, 1949-1967, undated; 6 (Box 2)
    - Botsford, Carolina (Romani), 1941-1951; 7 (Box 2)
    - Botsford, Carolina (Romani), 1952-1961; 14 (Box 3)
    - Botsford, Carolina (Romani), 1962-1966, undated; 9 (Box 4)
    - Botsford, Clarissa, Aubrey, Gianni and Joshua, 1966, undated; 2 (Box 4)
    - Botsford, F. "Baggie", 1947-1954 (Box 4)
    - Botsford, Richard V., 1945-1966; 5 folders (Box 4)
    - Botsford, Willard, 1939-1946; 2 (Box 4)
    - The Band of Botsford Bulletin, 1957-1958 (Box 4)
    - Bouge, L. J., 1951 (Box 5)
    - Brady, Ellen, 1949-1951 (Box 5)
    - Brinton, Jody, 1947 (Box 5)
    - Bromke, Del, 1943-1944 (Box 5)
    - Buckley, Mary, 1957 (Box 5)
    - Bunker, George, 1951-1954 (Box 5)
    - Burford, William, 1952 (Box 5)
    - Burr, Mona, 1957 (Box 5)
    - "C" General, 1951-1965; 3 (Box 5)
    - Cadel, Alberta, 1963-1964 (Box 5)
    - Callois, Roger, 1964-1965 (Box 5)
    - Campbell, Jean, undated (Box 5)
    - Canada Immigration Office, 1944-1946 (Box 5)
    - Cannon, B., 1951-1953 (Box 5)
    - Carlin, Frank, 1942-1944 (Box 5)
    - Carney, William, 1948-1949 (Box 5)
    - Carver, David, 1964-1966; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Caulfield, Peggy, 1959 (Box 5)
    - Center for the Study of Democratic Institutions, 1961 (Box 5)
    - Charles, Scott, 1962-1964; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - "Cher ami", 1962-1965 (Box 5)
    - Close, J. B., 1946-1947 (Box 5)
    - Coates, Carolyn, undated (Box 5)
    - Coffin, Catherine and Margot, undated (Box 5)
    - Collége de Paraphysique, 1953-1954 (Box 5)
    - Columbia University, 1958 (Box 5)
    - Congress for Cultural Freedom, 1960-1963, undated; 3 (Box 5)
    - Conkling, Woodbury, 1945-1946 (Box 5)
    - Copenhaven, Jane, 1948 (Box 5)
    - Cotnaréanu, Léon, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Covici, Pascal, 1961-1964; 2 folders (Box 5)
    - Cramer, Gérald, 1951 (Box 5)
    - Cummings, E. E., 1946 (Box 5)
    - "D" General, 1952-1964; 3 (Box 6)
    - Day Lewis, C., undated (Box 6)
    - De Beer, Jean, 1965 (Box 6)
    - De Laveleye, Renée, 1957 (Box 6)
    - Del Drago, G., 1949-1950 (Box 6)
    - Donadio, Candida, 1960-1964; 3 (Box 6)
    - Draper, Ted, 1961-1964; 2 folders (Box 6)
    - Dugdale, Grant, 1955-1956 (Box 6)
    - "E" General, 1946-1965; 3 (Box 6)
    - Eliot, T. S., 1946 (Box 6)
    - Enjuto, Jorge, 1960-1964; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Ellison, Ralph, 1957 (Box 6)
    - Etiemble, R., 1952 (Box 6)
    - "F" General, 1944-1964; 3 (Box 6)
    - Farrand, Roger A., 1963 (Box 6)
    - Fiedler, Leslie A., 1955 (Box 6)
    - Fjelde, Rolf, 1947-1955; 3 folders (Box 6)
    - Flanery, Nina, undated (Box 7)
    - Flores, Angel, 1960-1962; 2 folders (Box 7)
    - Fowlie, Wallace, 1944-1950 (Box 7)
    - Frechtman, Bernard, 1952 (Box 7)
    - Freeborn, Beatrice, 1955 (Box 7)
    - Freyre, Gilberto, 1962 (Box 7)
    - "Fulbright & other fellowships", 1956-1959 (Box 7)
    - Fulchignoni, Enrico, 1965 (Box 7)
    - "G" General, 1952-1965; 3 (Box 7)
    - Gaddis, William, 1957 (Box 7)
    - Gallo, Emmio, undated (Box 7)
    - Gaspard, Armand, 1962-1965 (Box 7)
    - "Gauguin correspondence", 1950-1953 (Box 7)
    - Gelfman, Herb, 1959-1960 (Box 7)
    - Gold, Herbert, 1957-1959 (Box 7)
    - Golffing, Francis, 1951 (Box 7)
    - Gordon, Don, 1945 (Box 7)
    - Greene, Helga, 1953-1964; 4 folders (Box 7)
    - Grossman, Bob, 1961-1964 (Box 7)
    - Guicharnaud, Jacques, 1957 (Box 7)
    - Guilloux, Louis, 1960-1961 (Box 7)
    - Gutierrez Heras, Joaquin, undated (Box 7)
    - "H" General, 1947-1965; 3 (Box 7)
    - Haight, Gordon S., 1945-1948 (Box 8)
    - Hamill, Peter, 1959-1961 (Box 8)
    - Hamilton, Iain, 1958-1963; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - Harcourt Brace & Co., 1953-1960; 2 (Box 8)
    - Harris, Harold, 1962-1964 (Box 8)
    - Heinemann, Beatrice, 1955 (Box 8)
    - Hoiby, Lee, 1958 (Box 8)
    - Holz, Georg, 1947-1961 (Box 8)
    - The Honorable Society of the Encyclopedia, 1962-1964 (Box 8)
    - Houseman, John, 1953-1961; 3 folders (Box 8)
    - "Houses", 1955-1959 (Box 8)
    - Hunt, John, 1961-1967, undated; 3 (Box 8)
    - Hurd, J., undated (Box 8)
    - Hutchins, Mr., 1961 (Box 8)
    - Hutchinson Group, 1958 (Box 8)
    - "I-J" General, 1947-1966 (Box 8)
    - Iglesias, Ignacio, 1961-1964; 2 (Box 8)
    - "Insurance", 1958 (Box 8)
    - Iowa State University, 1949-1950 (Box 8)
    - "Italy", 1957-1958 (Box 8)
    - Jacobs, Paul, 1962 (Box 9)
    - Jaesrich, Helmut, 1962-1964 (Box 9)
    - Jaffe, Herb, 1958-1961 (Box 9)
    - "Japan", 1958 (Box 9)
    - Javorsek, Joze, 1965; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Jelenski, Konstanty A., 1962-1965 (Box 9)
    - Johnson, Ulla, 1956-1964 (Box 9)
    - "Jobs", 1952-1958 (Box 9)
    - Josselson, M., 1961-1964; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Jotikasthira, Chewn, 1962-1964 (Box 9)
    - "K" General, 1951-1965; 3 (Box 9)
    - Kaiser, Lilo, 1953-1954 (Box 9)
    - Karlsruhe, Virginia, 1946-1947 (Box 9)
    - Kats, Ivan, 1962-1964; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - Keene, Donald, 1957-1958 (Box 9)
    - Kentfield, Calvin, 1957 (Box 9)
    - Khan, Hidayat, 1952 (Box 9)
    - "Kirgo", 1951 (Box 9)
    - Kolatsch, Myron, 1962-1963; 2 folders (Box 9)
    - "Kolokol", 1961, undated; 2 (Box 9)
    - "L" General, 1951-1965; 3 (Box 9)
    - Lafleur, Bruno, 1946-1955 (Box 9)
    - Lambert, Léon, 1945-1954 (Box 9)
    - Lasky, Melvin, 1962-1964 (Box 9)
    - Lawrence, Seymour, 1963-1964; 2 (Box 9)
    - Lekakis, Michael, undated (Box 9)
    - LeMay, Harding, 1958 (Box 9)
    - Levy, Ernst, 1948 (Box 9)
    - Librarie J. Vrin, Paris, 1961-1964 (Box 9)
    - Lorans, Kay, 1963 (Box 10)
    - Lowell, Robert and Elizabeth, 1962-1964; 4 (Box 10)
    - Lucci, Nobil Dona Alda Rangoni, 1963-1965 (Box 10)
    - Ludwig, Jack, 1958-1961 (Box 10)
    - Lytle, Andrew, 1955 (Box 10)
    - "M" General, 1948-1965; folders (Box 10)
    - Macready, Lady and Gen. Sir Gordon, undated (Box 10)
    - "Magazines", 1958 (Box 10)
    - McMahon, Thomas, 1947-1963; 4 folders (Box 10)
    - Malville, Guivi, 1950-1955 (Box 10)
    - Marshall, Margaret, 1955-1958 (Box 10)
    - Marshall, Rosamond, 1959 (Box 10)
    - Maud, Ralph, 1961 (Box 10)
    - Megnin, Joan, 1949-1950 (Box 10)
    - Mercier Vega, Luis, 1961-1964; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Milano, Paolo, 1953 (Box 10)
    - Miller, Henry, 1946 (Box 10)
    - Mills, Dot, undated (Box 10)
    - Mindlin, M., 1962-1964; 2 folders (Box 10)
    - Mishima, Yukio, 1958-1959 (Box 11)
    - Moffett, James, 1953-1957 (Box 11)
    - Monahan, Mr., 1963-1964; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - "Monastery", 1945-1950 (Box 11)
    - Monteallegre, Felicia, 1945 (Box 11)
    - Moore, Frank L., 1957 (Box 11)
    - William Morris Agency, Inc., 1955 (Box 11)
    - Müller-Landau, Rolf, 1948-1954 (Box 11)
    - Murena, H., 1962-1964 (Box 11)
    - Mutal, Silvio, 1963 (Box 11)
    - "N" General, 1946-1964; 3 (Box 11)
    - Nabokov, Nicolas, 1962 (Box 11)
    - Nardi, Gino, 1949-1953 (Box 11)
    - New Leader, 1963-1964 (Box 11)
    - New School, 1955-1956 (Box 11)
    - Noble Savage, 1959-1961; 2 folders (Box 11)
    - "O-R" General, 1947-1964; 2 (Box 11)
    - Oxenhandler, Neal, 1954 (Box 11)
    - Paiganker, K., undated (Box 11)
    - Pasinetti, P., 1954 (Box 11)
    - Patterson, David, 1945-1950 (Box 11)
    - Paz, Octavio, 1963 (Box 11)
    - Peyre, Henri, 1946-1954 (Box 12)
    - Podhoretz, Norman, 1964-1965; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Poetry New York, 1949-1950 (Box 12)
    - Poor, Bessie, undated (Box 12)
    - Portsmouth Priory, 1944-1958; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - "Priests, etc.", 1942-1944 (Box 12)
    - Preminger Jaffe Stuart Agency, 1958 (Box 12)
    - Puerto Rico, University of, 1958 (Box 12)
    - "Radio Corr.", 1958 (Box 12)
    - Rangoni, Jacques and Mary, 1952-1955 (Box 12)
    - Rangoni, Lucci and Alda, 1950-1957 (Box 12)
    - Recavarren, Jorge Luis, 1962-1964 (Box 12)
    - Reed, J. V., 1957 (Box 12)
    - Reid, Alastair, 1964; 2 folders (Box 12)
    - Richardson, Lawrence, 1945 (Box 12)
    - "Rockland", undated (Box 12)
    - Rodakiewicz, Erla, 1947-1957 (Box 12)
    - Rogers, Helen, 1962-1965 (Box 12)
    - Rosenblum, Jay, 1955 (Box 12)
    - Rosengren, Frank, 1946-1955 (Box 12)
    - Rousset, David, 1963-1964 (Box 12)
    - "S" General, 1946-1964; 3 (Box 12)
    - Saal, H., 1954 (Box 13)
    - Saint Lawrence, Sheila, 1958-1960 (Box 13)
    - Samson, Barbara, undated (Box 13)
    - Schlesinger, Arthur, 1962-1963 (Box 13)
    - Schneebaum, Tobias, 1955 (Box 13)
    - Sewell, Richard, undated (Box 13)
    - Shapiro, Harvey, 1946-1964; 4 folders (Box 13)
    - Shattuck, Roger, 1949-1964; 4 folders (Box 13)
    - Shelley, Robert, 1949-1950 (Box 13)
    - Sheperd, David, 1956 (Box 13)
    - Siegmund's Storage, 1963 (Box 13)
    - Smith, Corlies M., 1963-1964 (Box 13)
    - Spectorsky, Liz, 1960-1961 (Box 13)
    - Stephenson, Hally Wood, 1962-1964 (Box 13)
    - Stevens, Wallace, 1945 (Box 13)
    - Strauss, Helen, 1952-1954 (Box 13)
    - Stuckey, Bill, 1951 (Box 13)
    - Sturges, Sophie, 1944-1946 (Box 13)
    - "T" General, 1952-1963; 3 (Box 13)
    - Tató, Frances, 1959 (Box 13)
    - Tavernier, René, 1962-1965; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - Telos, Tom, undated (Box 13)
    - Thompson, John, 1962-1965; 2 folders (Box 13)
    - "U-V" General, 1947-1965; 2 (Box 14)
    - "U.S. Govt. Taxes", 1956 (Box 14)
    - United States Lines Company, 1951-1955 (Box 14)
    - Vanguard Press Inc., 1958 (Box 14)
    - Veillon, Yvonne, 1961-1964 (Box 14)
    - Viking Press Inc., 1961 (Box 14)
    - "W-Z" General, 1945-1965; 3 (Box 14)
    - Wanning, Andrews, undated (Box 14)
    - "Ward", undated (Box 14)
    - Warren, R. P., 1953-1955 (Box 14)
    - Watkins, Ann, 1954-1956; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Weekes, Zhiva, 1965-1966; 2 folders (Box 14)
    - Weiss, Renee, 1950-1960 (Box 15)
    - "Whodunit", 1958 (Box 15)
    - Winchester, Vera and Tarleton, 1949-1958 (Box 15)
    - Wingate, Alan, 1955 (Box 15)
    - Wilhelm, Jim, 1954 (Box 15)
    - Williams, William Carlos, 1946 (Box 15)
    - Winick, Charles, 1957 (Box 15)
    - Wood, Claire, 1957 (Box 15)
    - Yaddo, 1953-1955; 2 (Box 15)
    - Yaffe, James, 1958 (Box 15)
    - Yale University, 1944-1955 (Box 15)
    - Zygomala, A., 1952 (Box 15)
    - Other family correspondence, 1962, undated (Box 15)
    - "Miscellaneous unimportant hotel bills, money order rects., etc.", undated (Box 15)
    - Unidentified, 1947-1961; 10 (Box 15)
  - Third Party Correspondence and Other Papers
    Arranged alphabetically by author.
    Third Party Correspondence relates chiefly to International PEN and the Congress for Cultural Freedom. This subseries also includes a small amount of other papers: Botsford's curriculum vitae, schedules, and printed ephemera.
    - "A" General, 1963 (Box 16)
    - "B" General, 1962-1966 (Box 16)
    - "C" General, 1962-1966 (Box 16)
    - Carver, David, 1965 (Box 16)
    - "D" General, 1964-1965 (Box 16)
    - "G" General, 1963-1965 (Box 16)
    - "H" General, 1962 (Box 16)
    - "J" General, 1962-1965 (Box 16)
    - "K" General, 1965 (Box 16)
    - "L" General, 1962-1965 (Box 16)
    - "M" General, 1964-1965 (Box 16)
    - "N" General, 1961-1965 (Box 16)
    - "P" General, 1963-1965 (Box 16)
    - "R" General, 1965 (Box 16)
    - "S" General, 1964-1965 (Box 16)
    - "T" General, 1964 (Box 16)
    - "W" General, 1962-1966 (Box 16)
    - Unidentified, 1962-1963, undated (Box 16)
    - InterAmerican Committee, International Music Festival, Rio de Janiero, correspondence and other materials, 1963 (Box 16)
    - Lists of persons, questionnaires, information sheets, undated (Box 16)
    - Curriculum Vitae, typescript, undated (Box 16)
    - Newspaper clippings, undated (Box 16)
    - Printed material and ephemera, undated (Box 16)
    - Documents from correspondence file, 1949-1966 (Box 16)
    - Personal schedules, undated (Box 16)
- Writings, 1890-1968; Series II; 25.03 linear feet (65 boxes)
  Organized into nine subseries, by genre: Novels, Articles, Early Fiction and Short Stories, Essays, Notebooks, Poems, Screenplays, Translations, and Writings of Others.
  Series II includes drafts of many of Botsford's writings before 1968, including his first four published novels: The Master Race (1955), The Eighth-Best Dressed Man in the World (1957), Benveunto (1961), and The March-Man (1964). The series also contains drafts of articles, essays, poems, translations, and screenplays by Botsford. The Writings of Others subseries includes manuscripts by Charles Hull Botsford.
  - Novels
    Arranged alphabetically by title.
    - Benvenuto
      - Typescript and typescript carbon drafts, circa 1961; 3 (Box 17)
      - Typescript and autograph manuscript drafts, circa 1961; 7 (Box 18)
      - Typescript and typescript carbon drafts, corrected, circa 1961; 7 (Box 19)
      - Typescript drafts, corrected, circa 1961; 4 (Box 20)
      - Typescript drafts, circa 1961; 5 (Box 21)
      - Autograph manuscript, typescript and typescript carbon drafts, circa 1961; 4 (Box 22)
    - A Broken World, autograph manuscript draft and two typescript (carbon) copies, circa 1946; 9 (Box 23)
    - Carey's End
      - Typescript drafts, undated; 5 folders (Box 24)
      - Typescript drafts, undated; 4 folders (Box 25)
    - The Eighth-Best Dressed Man in the World
      - Autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, circa 1957; 4 (Box 26)
      - Typescript drafts and galley proof, circa 1957; 6 (Box 27)
      - Typescript drafts, circa 1957; 4 (Box 28)
      - Typescript drafts, circa 1957; 4 (Box 29)
    - The Index
      - Rejected or revised sections of drafts I and III, 1964-1965; 2 (Box 30)
      - Character sketches and other studies, undated; 9 (Box 31)
      - First draft, typescript, with various alternate and rejected versions, manuscript revisions and additions, undated; 3 (Box 32)
      - First draft, typescript, with various alternate and rejected versions, manuscript revisions and additions, undated; 2 (Box 33)
      - Second draft, typescript, pages 1-1395, with manuscript revisions and inserted additions, undated; 3 (Box 34)
      - Second draft, typescript, pages 1396-2499, with manuscript revisions and inserted additions, undated; 2 (Box 35)
      - Second draft, typescript carbon, partial copy, undated; 5 (Box 36)
      - Second draft, typescript carbon, partial copy, undated; 3 (Box 37)
      - Second draft, typescript (photocopy), pages 1-600, undated; 3 (Box 38)
      - Second draft, typescript (photocopy), pages 601-1300, undated; 3 (Box 39)
      - Second draft, typescript (photocopy), pages 1301-1950, undated; 3 (Box 40)
      - Second draft, typescript (photocopy), pages 1951-2499, undated; 3 (Box 41)
      - Second draft, typescript (photocopy), with corrections and additions, partial copy, undated; 4 folders (Box 42)
        Pages 1-182 with supplementary sections and an extra copy of pages 1-57 and 900-1413. Some pages missing in these sections.
      - Second draft, typescript (photocopy), with corrections and additions, partial copy, undated; 3 folders (Box 43)
        Scattered pages in 1500s and pages 1604-2100.
      - Second draft, typescript (photocopy), with corrections and ad+ditions, partial copy, undated; 2 folders (Box 44)
        Pages 2101-2498
      - Third draft, typescript, pages 1-599, with introductory material and unidentified draft sheets and notes, undated; 4 (Box 45)
      - Third draft, typescript, pages 600-1603, undated; 3 (Box 46)
      - Third draft, typescript (photocopy), pages 1-576, undated; 3 (Box 47)
      - Third draft, typescript (photocopy), pages 577-893, undated; 2 (Box 48)
      - Third draft, typescript (photocopy), pages 894-1279, undated; 3 (Box 49)
      - Third draft, typescript (photocopy), pages 894-1279, duplicate copy, undated; 3 (Box 50)
      - Fourth draft, typescript, corrected, pages 1-700, undated; 4 (Box 51)
      - Fourth draft, typescript, corrected, pages 701-989, undated; 3 (Box 52)
      - Typescript and typescript carbon drafts and notes, undated; 12 (Box 53)
    - Job: A Novel
      - Notes, typescript drafts and typescript carbon drafts, 1948; 6 (Box 54)
      - Typescript and typescript carbon drafts and alternate versions, undated; 2 (Box 55)
      - Rejected sections, autograph manuscript and typescript, 1948 (Box 81)
      - Prologue, autograph manuscript draft, undated (Box 81)
    - Kolokol "The Bell", typescript, autograph manuscript, and printed materials, 1960-1961; 4 (Box 56)
    - The March Man
      - Early drafts: autograph manuscript and typescript, corrected, circa 1964; 6 (Box 57)
      - Typescript and typescript carbon drafts, circa 1964; 6 (Box 58)
      - Typescript and typescript carbon drafts, galley proofs, circa 1964; 7 (Box 59)
    - The Master Race
      - Autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated; 5 (Box 60)
      - Typescript carbon drafts, 1953; 4 folders (Box 61)
      - Typescript carbon drafts, undated; 3 folders (Box 62)
      - Typescript drafts, undated; 5 folders (Box 63)
    - Matthew, undated
      - Autograph manuscript and typescript drafts, undated; 9 (Box 64)
      - Typescript and typescript carbon drafts, undated; 10 (Box 65)
    - The Old Believers, drafts and printed materials, 1959-1964, undated; 8 (Box 66)
    - Ozane, notes and drafts, 1963-1964; 8 folders (Box 67)
    - A Possession for the Bittern, typescript, corrected, 1947-1947; 2 (Box 68)
    - To Me It Is a Prison, autograph manuscript draft, 1945 (Box 81)
  - Articles
    The Articles subseries is further organized under two headings: Non-Fiction and Other Articles.
    - Non-Fiction
      Arranged alphabetically by title or topic.
      - [Article on Brazil], typescript, corrected, undated (Box 69)
      - "Borges Funicular," typescript and typescript carbon drafts, corrected, 1964 (Box 69)
      - "Borges Conversation," and "About Borges," typescript carbon, undated (Box 81)
      - "Cuba and Algeria: Two Revolutions," typescript carbon, 1963 September 17 (Box 69)
      - "Curriculum Vitae, Concise Bibliography," typescript and typescript carbon drafts, undated (Box 69)
      - "Francois Mitterand," typescript and typescript carbon drafts, 1965 (Box 69)
      - "Guided Tour, a television series with Keith Botsford," typescript carbon drafts, 1962 (Box 69)
      - [Interview with Amoedo,] typescript and typescript carbon, undated (Box 69)
      - "A Letter from the Provinces of Mexico," typescript and typescript carbon, 1963 (Box 69)
      - "A Matter of Jurisdiction: The Hearing at San Juan," printed version (photocopy), 1960 (Box 69)
      - "A Member of the Delegation," typescript, undated (Box 69)
      - "Oscar Lewis: Pedro Martinez ," typescript and typescript carbon drafts, 1964 (Box 69)
      - "Out in the Styx: A Letter on Latin America," typescript carbon and galley proofs, 1965 (Box 81)
      - Review of Modern Brazilian Poetry, typescript, undated (Box 69)
      - "Torre-Nilson," typescript drafts, undated (Box 81)
      - Review of Venezuela's Democratic Revolution, typescript and typescript carbon drafts and correspondence, 1965 (Box 69)
      - "Youngers and Olders," typescript (photocopy) and printed version (photocopy), undated (Box 69)
    - Other Articles
      - "Anatomy of a Party," research material, typescript, undated (Box 70)
      - "Aprismo Without the Apra," typescript and typescript carbon, 1962 June 16 (Box 70)
      - "Ash Wednesday in Brazil," typescript, 1962 March (Box 70)
      - "Belaunde," typescript, 1962 June (Box 70)